<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nations right in Magna Charta discussed with the thing called Parliament. Whereas I Theaurau John tendred a petition dated the 15 November 1650. To the Parliament so called; there is a name and a thing, and a thing, and a name, and a name, and not the thing, and the name and the thing both in one according to the obedience to the thing and name. I tendred my petition upon the declarative: it was but name to me, and not the thing, which caused this inquiry to be made, and to be declared that the people may see and discerne betwixt the name and the thing. / Written by me Theaurau Iohn Tannijjour Hipriest sabbah scribah jail Earl of Exex or otherwise Essex tenet of Norway or Normandi Lord Paulet of Sene in France.</title>
            <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T154A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E621_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865556</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E621[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nations right in Magna Charta discussed with the thing called Parliament. Whereas I Theaurau John tendred a petition dated the 15 November 1650. To the Parliament so called; there is a name and a thing, and a thing, and a name, and a name, and not the thing, and the name and the thing both in one according to the obedience to the thing and name. I tendred my petition upon the declarative: it was but name to me, and not the thing, which caused this inquiry to be made, and to be declared that the people may see and discerne betwixt the name and the thing. / Written by me Theaurau Iohn Tannijjour Hipriest sabbah scribah jail Earl of Exex or otherwise Essex tenet of Norway or Normandi Lord Paulet of Sene in France.</title>
                  <author>Tany, Thomas, fl. 1649-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "January 1 1650".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Magna Carta --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE NATIONS RIGHT in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> diſcuſſed with the thing Called Parliament.</head>
            <p>Whereas I <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>urau John</hi> Tendred A Petition dated the 15 of <hi>November</hi> 1650. To the Parliament ſo called; There is a name and a thing, and a thing, And a name, And a name, And not the thing, And the Name and the thing both in one according to the Obedience to the thing and name.</p>
            <p>I Tendred my petition upon the declarative: It was but Name to me, And not the thing, which cauſed this inquiry to be made, And to be declared that the people may ſee and diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Name and the thing.</p>
            <p>Written by me <hi>Theaurau Iohn</hi> Tannijjour Hiprieſt ſabbah ſcribah Jail Earl of <hi>Exex</hi> or otherwiſe <hi>Eſſex</hi> Tenet of <hi>Norway</hi> or <hi>Normandi</hi> Lord Paulet of <hi>ſene</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> John Tanni true Earl of <hi>Exex</hi> alias <hi>Eſſex</hi> of the ſeed roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deſentive from <hi>Aaron</hi> the Lords Hipreeſt, deſentive from true right Henry the ſeventh, which was of the raſe of the <hi>Iews,</hi> of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> line, As my record of my Gencoligie, will make appear from <hi>Aaron Moſes</hi> brother; Here is a myſtery in this ſeeming ſeeing age, yet never more deeds of darkneſſe acted by the ſonnes of men</p>
            <p>Whereas I having laid my claim to the crown of <hi>England</hi> before any Acts came forth by the members that are members, I deny all that be, to be in the being, for he cannot properly be ſaid to be, that is unradaxed; That is ſtands not in and upon the foundation that gives a being to them all, and us all, that is <hi>Magna Charra,</hi> and the petition of right; for mind; it is not names, but things that is conſiſtant with the good of the nation: for a name is not the thing but the thing is the name and thing. So are not you that call your ſelves a Parliament. For to make your name true, it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117801:2"/>muſt be declarative Acts done by you, yet if it were ſo you are unradiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men in your conjunct as after I will ſhew not wronging you one tittle, nor any one for Truth is a direct rule meaſuring all, unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring none which is. Now not any Act that you cauſe to be publiſhed can cut off, or leſſen that that is. For that That is truth the ſayings of men cannot unſay it; Theirs is but lettered names. But it is the Thing and will be. Becauſe it hath a being. The name none. You make an act to be death to claime the crown in Charles Stuarts Line. Now what I have clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is from Henry the true ſeventh. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as that villane 8 Henry hath ſet them to make his title good. By which treepwhole Stuart came in; yet he is a A Cheat in that name Stuart; which I can declare, and weaken the Ly. For I count him no better when Truth ſhall have her reſurrection: Now my claime was paſt before your Act came forth; And now you ſhall ſee I ſhall ſtoop to your will (Not Law) And in obedience to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, this you can make no claime to the crown of <hi>England;</hi> But to that Command I ſtate this full ſaying; WHAT I HAVE WRITTEN, I HAVE WRITTEN; I beſeech you all people take notice of this ſtate, And judge whether ſince the act I have laid any claim to the crown of <hi>England,</hi> yet I take your commanding negative to be a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ifie to my affirmative, and ſo by ſtate I looſe nothing. For truth is truth: ſo much for the firſt.</p>
            <p>Now know I come as. Nay a Commonwealths-man-Nay the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths-man, and head of your Houſe by my Barrony of Oxon 'tis ſtated Oundell in Northampton in Buckingham-ſhire; to let you know the meaning of that ſtate; tis thus. That villian Henry the 8 ſo called to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Aſſinant. Stated it in two Counties. That if claime was made in one, it lay in the other: So this was the indendant cheate. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe repealed that Act of Richard the firſt and third, And made it death to challenge any one into the field, and ſtate place and day: Now I have challenged both the Marques of Herford, and the Earl of Northumberland by letter, &amp; he thatmade that ſtatute to preſerve his wicked ſeed God hath made it deſtructive. For they are challenged by that, that they ſhould be defended by as he thought and it is death for them to anſwer by his own law, The challenge to Northumberland is in my brother <hi>Oliver Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells</hi> right as he is heir aparant to Deavon and Northumberland: Onely Northumberland hath my vicountcie as I ſhall make appear Now as I am a commoner of <hi>England.</hi> Now I ſtare that ſtate Eſſentiall none can deny, and in this ſtate you are bound to me: Now we ſhall, and all capacities look on, and into the queſtion, and ſtate ſtated: Now know that your being and my being in that right of rights. Nay that divine right inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant to all: 'Its Eſſentiall, wherein your and mine is but one: Now comes the ſtate of your being; being in right of, Nay in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that is your life, and mine, and the nations, all conjoyned into one: Now in that one, all being right, out of, and from that radax: know that in that right the Major, includes the Minor; Then where is your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the nation, and that, that gave you a being; The Major choſe the Minor, not to Lord but to love, Right redreſſe; and ſuppreſſe: now in the word ſuppreſſe we ſee powerful actings to all our griefs, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117801:2"/>love &amp; redreſſe ſhut out of door, is this the end you were choſen for? or that end our Fathers for our good cauſed ſuch a compoſure, that though they were dead, the life of their right deſcentive might live in us and we in it; Alas we are the name, but they were the Thing and name truely: we are nothing in that ſtock; for every mans right is in, and by, and at a few mens wills: it is death to ſpeak trueth which is the Thing, only we live in the name, which name is a ly without the thing.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the true ſtate of this our called Parliament fellow-Commoners that cannot offend, if you underſtand your own Eſſence, ye were choſen but the choiſe at firſt was not perfect; conſiſtant with the intendant of our Radaxes; there ought not in that choiſe parties to be made to make a choiſe, but a free voluntary intendant was intended:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> beſeech you brethren if you Be, yea will hear trueth if you cannot do it be aſſenters to it, and not oppoſers of it, in ſo doing you will be found fighters againſt the Lord of hoſts, whoſe breath is in you if you be in the trueth, I meaſure no man I hate no man, only the Lord hath cauſed me to lay down to you the rule to meaſure your ſelves by, if you be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that it is trueth follow after it, and inſue it and break off your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by righteous Actions, that the broken may be healed; For this I know great wrath is gone forth from the Lord: Now to grant you were a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſet acting for the intending, you were choſen, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and abuſed and the Nations right not only vilifide, deſtroyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Nations choiſe was called forth then be came you another thing, and no Parliament according to the antient right of Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the Petition of right that hath its eſſential right in and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om <hi>Magna Charta:</hi> there this is your proper ſtate, you were no Parliament, that though you in heart were right members, for the heart makes the right member of a true aſſembly. This is an alluſive allegory, but to ſtate it home, you were in truth your ſervants ſervants and no Parliament according to the antient right of <hi>Magna Carta,</hi> and the ſecond petition of right in King James his time. Now according to the right of our right there muſt be an account rendered for the invading all our Rights in that ſtate; O it had been a glorious work that then a new choiſe had been according to true election, then was the time to have made us a free people as you call us, but your calling us free, we cannot ſay Amen, but we may ſafely affirm we are worſe bound, And you now can not help us, nor your ſelves, Nor can never recover: I know in what ſtate this ſtands, but I conſeal. Now to ſpeak proper you were the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers thing called a Parliament: Now to them you proved the name, and not their intending thing, For then they thought you ſhould do right to them and they would do Right to you, and you two held all our Rights by force from us: If you, or they or both had cauſed a new choiſe: not that you had power by right to ſtand, and chuſe to you: but the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtanding defenſive, having let the right down from you into the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple again in whom it is inhearent, and you have put your ſelves in hazard of the New chooſing again; which thing you ought to have done: And I need not let you know this; for you know too much in doing no more: Now it is juſt that they that wronged the Nation in their right, ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117801:3"/>be wronged by them they wrongfully ſet up to have their right by, not regarding the Nations wrong it ſuffers by them: Now I ſpeak as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner of England, nay I ſpeake for the whole Native: It is a diſhonour to you that the ſouldier is not paid fully to a penny 'tis his due, yea much hardſhip have they ſuffered for nothing. Now I beſeech you conſider that when a Parliament is, it doth right maintaining the honour of the Nation in all its proper eſſences: Now I hope I ſhall offend none that truly Are, for they that Be will endure looking into: for truth ſeeks no covert nor Corner, but ſtands openly to be viewed of all and viewes all; mind that ſtate: But falſehood and a ly is ſeeking coverts continually, and alwaies building defenſives, and yet never ſtrong, but alwaies weake and fearful: The Righteous is as bold as a Lyon walkes in, and by one and the ſame rule: Now if that rule which is here intendant be all your meaſures, or the Major part, then fear will not poſſeſſe you. But if ye be wicked, that is weakneſſe, and ſoon offended: But 'tis better to return though to the Manhood diſgrace, then to go on in ſtubborneſſe in an evil way, and reſolve thus, that though we have done thus, and conſcience witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, we will cut off to eſtabliſh our own way not Gods way: Then know that guilt will never be ſecured, but will cut off all, but it ſelf: This is the true nature of rebellion againſt the Command of God: That word true is not proper ſtated in that ſence, becauſe trueth cannot be in a ly; for nothing but trueth confounds the ly: Now to returne, to you whom is intended thus much; if you ſay a Parliament, I ſay the diſgrace of the Nation; Thus will you ſtand to your words, your vowes, your Oathes, your Covenant, your ingagement, now I know ſome of the leaſt Actors can with innocency, and uprightneſſe ſtand to it. Now while it is thus, the upright, and innocent ſuffers, for God hath a people among you, who are of a trembling heart, and now theſe ſuffer, through the miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages of others, &amp; are branded with the name of infamie: But my Brethren, God will clear you in the day of reſtitution (and it is at hand) Now if men dare not own their word, Oathes, Covenant, Engagement, nor ſtand by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> theſe men muſt be ſpirits; and not men, yet we ſee and feel theſe to be men; but if they do diſown that is ſtated: judge ye, are they fitted to be ſuch men? know, ſo much as a man is juſt, he is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative of his makers majeſty and no farther: For your words let the Nation judge, which truely is eſſential, your Judges hold the ſame method in the firſt ſtate, as the Major choſe the Minor, I hope we that have ſtood for trueth may now ſpeak trueth, though we cannot injoy it: your word and our adherents to you in the firſt, was for the Goſpel, the Law, the liberty of the ſubject, we that are the Commons: you having overcome by our vaſte charge, loſſe, and trouble what hath been injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of this by us yet? but thus we have paid your requeſt: I mean taxes, you have deducted the fouldiers pay for his quarter in part, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try hath had this by the ſouldier eaten up, and no pay; whoſe wide purſe holds that ſumme that was worſe then ten taxes together: this I know I felt, and from fence I ſpeak only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now I blame not the ſouldier for this; but you, named Parliament: One more to that when all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion was ſpent, there comes another reckoning, the Excize-man he muſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117801:3"/>have ſo much for beer and meat, that was eaten by your, nay our owne ſouldiers; and never a penny for the ſubſtance, but ſo much for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the ſouldier, with parting with that we have for nothing; is this a demonſtrative of a true Parliament, I deſire no offence may be taken of truth for what I have writ I will maintain, and ſend the leaſt Meſſenger, or porter I will appear and anſwer by writing; for I have an impeade in my ſpeech, and I deſire noe more favour: for truth is truth and will be though trod on: I am not thus chaſtiſed to run into a corner, if he whom I ſerve will not deliver me, I am content, ſo that deliverance come but to the poor peeled Nation, though I be offered a ſacrifice, and burnt to aſhes for them I ſhall rejoice: he cannot be that I am, but muſt be ſo in the reality of his ſould before the eternal God: know you, I know what I ſpeak, though this ſtate you cannot reach: So much for the firſt freedome.</p>
            <p>The next is to maintain the Law of the Land, and pull down tyranny, this we were ſworn to: Now what law is there preſerved but all deſtroyed? for <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is the being of all our beings; if we have then beings in the true right of the Nation; in which being ye aſſembled have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and then ye which have no being, tis impoſſible for you to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a being to us that are (if we durſt ſay) in the right being, and ye in the wrong being: for you Be not for us; but ours: I pray mind this the intention is good, if right conſtrued: can you ſay you are for us? Tis ſaying indeed, that ſaying ſtands you in little, there is the price you pay for us; but prey upon us by conſequence, doth this ſtand in full with your Covenant of pulling down Tiranny? Know tiranny is not a name, but the Thing: We cut of Charles for tiranny, it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writes a ſad motto amongſt Tirants. Now what is a Tirant: An Oppreſſor, an Incrocher, a Conjoiner to himſelf of that, that is not his, againſt that Thing the Nation covenanted, not the name of tiranny, but the Thing: now where that Thing reignes in its ſphear, the Nation is bound by Oath to take it down or elſe they are perjured men, and covenant-breakers, and let all the earth know covenant-breakers God will judge: For the preſervation of the Law, we have none made; know you that an act or law, takes its birth at your riſing, or diſſolving, and not before: Now good men may be made bad by ſitting too long, and the cuſtome of Parliament was that the laſt ſhould reform the firſt, if any miſcarage was in the foregoing ſtate, and add what good, they in their wiſdome thought good for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: But we ſit ſo cloſe, ſo long that it gives a cauſe of jealouſy we are afraid that others ſhould ſee what we have done: is truth aſhamed that her acts ſhould be looked into? 'Tis not truth that is ſo: The next and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, the influence of the people is wholly depopulated, in all their eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial liberties, ſo that <hi>Magna Charta</hi> which was their koatrified ſtrength, now 'tis of no uſe at all to them: now to deal plainly with you, if <hi>Magna Charta</hi> takes being, and life, it can no waies, but by deſtruction of one or both, that is the Parliament or people: Sirs it is heavy, and lamentable I mourn to ſee it, yet cannot help it: happy is he whoſe hands and heart is not defiled with bloud, for bloud muſt, and will have bloud: now what is wanting? Why love, What is Love? It is God; What is God? A King and he cannot raigne over bloud-thirſty men: now know that king is but a name, and not the Thing, and king is the name and the Thing: The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117801:4"/>is not king, but the anointing is the king, But this method is not known among you, for if it were better actions would flow: I know my afflictions you have heard of, I have bin made hands, feet, food, eyes, and clothing to many: I have been emptied of temporalls, but am filled with the eternall being, which hath loved me with everlaſting love: now know I hate no mans perſon, I envy none, I care for none, I am One, and that One that ſtate what you, nay the creation can, in earth, aire, fire, water, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial, Caeleſtial, the influences of the ſtars, I am able to anſwer, to give an account, I am able to give a ſtate, in theſe things in anyone of theſe things, that the whole creation cannot anſvver, if they could I could not be high Prieſt to my God.</p>
            <p>I have put 3 ſmall queries on this little manuſcript that by them I may know it to be my one.</p>
            <p>What is the creative part of the Cabaleſterial inclue in the Terreſteriall Orbs of the Theabarick: that word is Calde.</p>
            <p>What is the inclue of Philiades in her coertive part in the new Trine in the Hemiſpheer of ſol that word new ſeems ſtrange, but to let you know there is a new birth in the Planitoriam ſcheme, or ſcine.</p>
            <p>What is the incluſive PERTINEAT in the conclave of the medeterranean Aſſome: Scholers look to PERTINEAT, I am but a childe yet, and but 9 weeks ſince God gave me this childiſh knowledge, yet with my child ſhneſſe I deſire you bear with me: Now know that anger is weakneſſe; And wrath that is not God: but by God it is. Minde but That ſtate laſt: Now for you to be angry becauſe I do not give you the name of Parliament, It is becauſe you ſhould not be deſtroyed: Wiſdome foreſees the dangerous event that will fall on you in that ſtate: your method and rule, hath been all along evaſions: Now I will helpe you to the beſt, yet it will not help you: For though I koatrefie you there, you fall in another place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, but made by your ſelves. Now I ſpeak as a Commoner, that ſtate cannot be denied me, And in that ſtate I being it is for the Reall, not intentive good I take the vvhole to ſpeak for. As I am the head of your convene, (if ye were) by my Barrony of Oxon alias Eſſex: Now I have two rights, nay three rights to ſtand on, and for: for <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the being of our Beings, and a commoner in that right in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> the head of you, if you were: Now how can any ſtate be ſtated betwixt that, that hath an eſſential being, And that that hath none? To make good that ſtate of Evaſion, I promiſed to you, it is thus: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth cannot in reall truth call you to an account, Neither ought they if you deny that name Parliament, which if you affirme you undo your ſelves: Thus to be accountable to that, from whence you had no being in their being, nor being by them, nor from them: but this ſtate you muſt bear with, your being is of, and upon them; Remember this ſtate was cited in the foregoing page ſpeaking of God; This is myſterious, but I ſtate my method to the reach and overture of your Capacities: Now according to the reall rule of right, the common-wealth ſhould render it ſelfe ridiculous to demand a due where they committed no truſt: your negative is truer then their affimative in this ſtate: this is a ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that all our Eſtates are waſted, oppreſſion goes on, and muſt go
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117801:4"/>on; Though it is ſtrange, tis true, the ſenſatives can ſet to their ſeal: I would it were other waies.</p>
            <p>But to finde out this Thing that BEES upon us all: there it is we may ſwear Thing, we feele it: Now to finde this BEE, that BEES every where amongſt us: I have found it firſt: I bring tidings: For this Thing ſake am I ſent forth to undeceive the people, tis the ſouldiers intended right Thing to himſelfe. He gave it a being: and the Thing that he thought ſhould haue been in a ſence life to him, is proved death in a ſence: for the Thing, nay his Thing proves but name, and that name in that credit, that when he hath done his duty to his Thing, he thought it would have proved, and in his accounts he ſinds it Thing, and in deduction for his quarter, and by that his ſum cut leſſe, and then counting at his agreement at 8 d. a day, for which many out of conſcience havedeſtroyed them, and theirs and coming to their Thing, it is but name, and the name baring no more credit to him then to be worth to him 4 ſhil. a pound; Is this payment for faithfull ſervice: judge all men ſouldiers this is truth you know: my heart bleeds to ſee, but cannot help it: unlawfull, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt wayes is ever paide in its own coine, and ſo tis juſt; your full ſums agreed of, is your due, as God is juſt, for there is a juſtneſſe in the meean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thing and that is properly called Gods eſſentiall being (I ſpeak after the manner of men) now ſouldiers by creating your Parliament, if you can call it ſo, it matters not to me: to me name is not; but things are the ſubſtance: now though for the preſent your monies would not make much of it a bove 4 ſhil a pound, it vvould be inquired into now the cauſe came that procured the effect of your ſail of your due earned debt; was it weaknes in your radax, that it was note able to ſtate a ſtrong eſſence, that muſt be denyed; for their power and your power would have ſetched in your own dues, being the whole kingdome was under your commands But it might be thus: In writing I can make the laſt letter take the whole ſtate, when I write in Mophes, that is in the Mediſh method then I write k for coffe which is ſtrong now from a radax; I can let fall a weak eſſence, to take the ſtate in k to the radax again: I am afraid of this jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling nay plain dealing: I will prove it the ſouldier is neceſſitated through you, he is forced to ſell, you muſt be paymaſters your derivacies draws up into eſſencie; your eſſencie, and ye ſtate the radax of the ſouldiers earned wages: is it fair or foule let the world judge: true tis undeniable; hovv comes ſuch an involved inrolement of ſouldiers dues into a payment, for whoſe lands I know not, but the ſouldiers due is the true due in that patched pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe; Now ſouldiers I muſt ſhow you your undues: for I have but one rule; you wronged the Commonwealth, when you devided the Parliament, then you erred as is hinted before: Now whereas ye ſouldiers wronged the Nation in their right, you are rewarded with wrong by your own intended right; now to do the nation wrong, having done ſo, you ought to do the Nation right, for that end you vvere ſet on worke: Now to do right to the Nation, is all you can do, take down your Thing ſet up by you: that Thing nay name Parliament, and let the right deſcend into the people again, and a new choice made, theſe to be accountable to you, becauſe they had a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and from and by you, in this doing you prove your ſelves, nay they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117801:5"/>cauſe you prove your ſelves honeſt men at laſt, now this way wil prove good for the nation; Onely the loſſe of their moneyes: thus you may account with them, that have ſo ſtraightly accounted with you: take your due where it is due to be taken: for your due God doth know is deerly earned, and juſtly ought to have been paide you natives know, tis not the ſouldier that wrongs you, love the ſouldier, none can help you but he, tis he that ſhould pay the ſouldiers that wrongs you, who that is judge ye: now if any man or men be offended at this truth here inſerted, and count me an enemy to the Parliament: know I cannot properly nor unproperly be an enemy to that that truly is not the Thing but a name, nay death to them by law in and by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to own the ſame according to the right of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons right; a Parliament is the glory of the nation, Nay the truth of the Nation; tis the ſplendor and beauty of our beauty, if by us it hath a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or elſe it can be no Parliament, now this I honour, and would lay down my life for, as at firſt I ſtood for you, when you were, and covenanted with you, and held with you till you from lambs turned wolves, then I was afraide of you, I oppoſed Charles Stuart in ſhip money was committed for it in <hi>London,</hi> my horſe taken, and ſold for ſhipmony in Cambrige ſhire; by Pitcher of Trumpington then ſheriffe, know I ever ſtood againſt the Thing Tyranny, and not the name, now I hope no man, no honeſt man or men, will conceive anger againſt me for ſpeaking the truth, as this I leave to all men to judge of, But thus in plain termes, if any man, or men be angry and charge me with crime, This I declare to all peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, that, that Man or men I vvill prove traitor, or traitors by the law of the land, by word, by promiſe, by proteſtation, by oath, by covenant, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, All this I will do ſo ſure as the Lord lives, I jeſt not, I am in True earneſt. Look to it, I weep for it, to your conſciences I commit to judge of: But know a Ly with a Ly is one Meathod, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> one Meathod. But bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be meaſured by, Truth then it will not hold, ſo much for this time.</p>
            <p>Now know I am a mad man; And ye declare me ſo to be, it will be weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in you to queſtion me; But know that A mad man is not to anſwer, by the law of the land: I take that privilige, you cannot deny it, if you be men ſenſable bare with my v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kneſſe; God I hope vvill give me greater underſtanding: ſo I reſt your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at are truely the Lords; that ſear him, and vvalke in obeeience to him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours To ſerve you in love Theaurau John Tani.</signed>
               <dateline>From the three Golden Lions without Temple-bar.
<date>December 28. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
